Finding Aid for Vice President for Government Relations (University of Michigan) records, 1960-1999
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Vice President for Government Relations (University of Michigan) records
1960-1999
University of Michigan. Vice-President for Government Relations.
87420 Bimu B6 2
Office established in 1968 as the Vice-President for State Relations and Planning; reorganized and name changed in 1974 with the appointment of Richard L. Kennedy who already had the position of University Secretary. University Secretary became a separate office following Kennedy's retirement in 1994. Files relating to the University's liaison with state government agencies, including budget and appropriations materials; also topical files and materials documenting the communication process between the University and the state, and slides; also files of the university's office in Washington, D.C.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
38 linear feet
The record group Vice President for Government Relations (Donor No. 7446 ) arrives in periodic accessions. Some records were also received from the former office Vice President for University Relations (Donor No. 8041).
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The Vice President for Government Relations records are open for research except for certain records restricted by statute or university policy.
The Vice President for Government Relations record group includes restricted material in the following categories:
Personnel Related Records -- removed to vault storage.
The Board of Regents in their January 1968 meeting approved the creation of the new position of Vice President for State Relations and Planning. This office was created as a response to the increasing costs of, as well as increasing demand for, higher education, in addition to keener competition for funds. The office was to serve as the focal point for the development of academic programs and capital plans within the university, and as an instrument for articulating these plans to the government of the state of Michigan. In addition, this office was to serve as the chief consultant to the President and all other vice presidents of the university on questions related to state government planning and relations. Previously, all of these functions had been carried out by a number of different units within the university.
Arthur M. Ross, former Commissioner of Labor Statistics for the United States Department of Labor, was appointed Vice President for State Relations and Planning effective July 1, 1968. Ross passed away suddenly in June 1970, and Fedele F. Fauri, Dean of the School of Social Work, was appointed as his successor. Fauri served in this position until his retirement in September 1974, whereupon the office was reorganized under the leadership of Richard L. Kennedy, Secretary of the University. Kennedy held the dual title Vice President for State Relations and Secretary of the University.
At the November 1984 Board of Regents meeting, the office's name was changed from Office of State Relations to the Office of Government Relations (the bylaws were formally amended in September 1985). Following Kennedy's retirement in 1994, the office was once again reorganized. The Secretary of the University functions handled by Kennedy were created as a separate office (Harold Johnson served as interim secretary prior to the appointment of Roberta Palmer). Walter Harrison, who had been appointed Vice President for University Relations, was given oversight of a unit that included associate vice presidents for government relations (community, state, and federal), Marketing and Communications, News and Information Services, and radio station WUOM.
In January 1998 the Regents approved a recommendation to return functions of the Secretary of the University to the Vice President for University Relations. Shortly thereafter, in May 1998, Harrison accepted the presidency of the University of Hartford. After Harrison's departure, at the recommendation of President Bollinger, University Relations was divided into three vice presidential posts: Vice President for Government Relations, Vice President and Secretary, and Vice President for Media Relations. The last position eventually became Vice President for Communications and was staffed by Lisa Rudgers in April 2000.
Cynthia Wilbanks was named Vice President for Government Relations in 1998. In January 2002 she was also asked to serve as interim Vice President for Development following the departure of Susan Feagin. The current arrangement of the office has a federal relations director, community relations director, Lansing service center director, and shared oversight for a state outreach director. Current information about this office is available on the Web at the following URL: http://www.umich.edu/~govrel/
The University of Michigan Washington Office was formally opened in January 1990. It was created to establish a permanent presence in Washington and function as an outreach base to Congress and the federal government in support of the university's teaching, research, and service.
The records of the Office of Vice President for Government Relations reflect the core functions of the office (local, state, and federal government relations and planning) and the various incarnations of the office, including the duties of Secretary of the University variously performed by the office. Documentation is primarily from the Ann Arbor campus office, but also includes files on the federal relations office operated by the university in Washington, D.C. Files received directly from the state relations office in Lansing are not included here. Materials detail the budget and appropriations process, interaction with community, state and federal legislators, and lobbying and monitoring efforts in Washington, D.C. on issues such as research funding, student loans, and support for higher education. The records are physically arranged in the manner in which they arrived in the archives. In this finding aid the records are described by their intellectual organization and similar material for the various accessions is described and listed together. Researchers should note that later accessions often extend records series and topics from prior accessions.
The records of the University of Michigan Office of the Vice President for Government Relations and Secretary of the university have been divided into the following series of material: University Budget, Topical Files, Office Assignments and Communication Records, Special Topical Files, Correspondence Files, Evolution of the Office, Audio-Visual Materials, Washington Office Files, and Vice President for University Relations Correspondence,.
Subjects:
Tax and expenditure limitations--Michigan.; University of Michigan--Administration.; University of Michigan--Finance.; University of Michigan. Vice-President for Government Relations.; University of Michigan. Secretary.; Fauri, Fedele Frederick, 1909-; Kennedy, Richard L.; Ross, Arthur M., 1916-1970.; University of Michigan. Secretary.; University of Michigan. Vice-President for State Relations and Planning.
Genre Terms:
Photographic slides.
- University Budget, 1968-1999
  The University Budget series, 1968 to 1980, contains chronologically arranged records (and then arranged alphabetically within the span of years.) The bulk of the material consists of files related to the liaison process with state government agencies regarding the university's operating budget during these years. Included for most years are appropriations requests, capital outlay budget requests, documentation pertaining to the various requests, and materials documenting legislative budget hearings.
  - 1968-1980, 6 linear feet
    - 1968-1969
      - Appropriations Request-General (Box 1)
      - Capital Outlay Request (Box 1)
    - 1969-1970
      - Appropriations Request
        - General (Box 1)
        - Gerontology, Institute of (Box 1)
        - Medical School Special Request (Box 1)
        - University Hospital-Psychiatric Division (Box 1)
      - Capital Outlay Request (Box 1)
      - Governor's Recommendation (Box 1)
      - House Appropriations Committee (Box 1)
      - Operating Request (Box 1)
      - Response to State Budget Office Guidelines (Box 1)
      - Senate Appropriations Committee (Box 1)
      - Supplemental Information to Request for Appropriation (Box 1)
    - 1970-1971
      - Appropriations-General (Box 1)
      - Appropriations Request
        - Ann Arbor Campus (Box 1)
        - Dearborn Campus (Box 1)
        - Gerontology, Institute of (Box 1)
        - University Hospital-Psychiatric Division (Box 1)
      - Budget Bureau (Box 1)
      - Capital Outlay (Box 2)
      - Documentation, 3 folders (Box 2)
      - Flint (Box 2)
      - General, 3 folders (Box 2)
      - Governor's Office (Box 2)
      - House Appropriations Committee (Box 2)
      - Legislative Fiscal Agency (Box 2)
      - Senate Appropriations Committee (Box 2)
    - 1971-1972
      - Appropriations Request
        - Ann Arbor Campus (Box 2)
        - Dearborn Campus (Box 2)
        - Flint Campus (Box 2)
      - Budget Needs (Box 2)
      - Documentation, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - 1972-1973
      - Appropriations Request-Ann Arbor Campus
        - Budget Cycle (Box 2)
        - Budget Needs-Conference with Governor, November 22, 1971 (Box 2)
        - Documentation, 3 folders (Box 2)
        - Incremental Program Budget Request (Box 2)
        - Institutional Budgets-Ann Arbor, Dearborn, Flint (Box 2)
        - Legislative Fiscal Agency Staff Hearings, February 14, 1972 (Box 2)
    - 1973-1974
      - Bureau of Budget Program Budget Hearing, October 27, 1972 (Box 3)
      - Capital Outlay Request-Ann Arbor, Dearborn, and Flint Campuses (Box 3)
      - Conference with Governor Milliken, December 20, 1972 (Box 3)
      - Documentation, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - Enrollment Audit (Box 3)
      - General, 4 folders (Box 3)
      - House Appropriations Committee Hearing, July 5, 1973 (Box 3)
      - House and Senate Fiscal Agencies Documentation (Box 3)
      - Legislative Fiscal Agency Staff Hearings, February 1972 (Box 3)
      - Legislative Fiscal Analysts' Visit, October 9-11, 1972 (Box 4)
      - Legislative-General (Box 4)
      - Program Budget Request
        - Dearborn Campus (Box 4)
        - Flint Campus (Box 4)
        - Gerontology, Institute of (Box 4)
        - Mental Health (Box 4)
      - Senate Appropriations Committee Hearing, May 14, 1973 (Box 4)
      - Senate Appropriations Subcommittee-Supplemental Information, March 27, 1974 (Box 4)
    - 1974-1975
      - Budget Cycle (Box 4)
      - Budget Request
        - Ann Arbor Campus (Box 4)
        - Dearborn Campus (Box 4)
        - Flint Campus (Box 4)
        - Gerontology, Institute of, and Mental Health (Box 4)
      - Bureau of Budget Program Revision Request Discussion, October 24, 1973 (Box 4)
      - Capital Outlay Request-Ann Arbor, Dearborn, and Flint Campuses, and Medical Center (Box 4)
      - General, 3 folders (Box 5)
      - House Appropriations Subcommittee for Higher Education Hearing, January 30, 1974 (Box 5)
      - House of Representatives (State of Michigan) (Box 5)
      - Senate (State of Michigan) (Box 5)
      - Senate Appropriations Subcommittee for Higher Education Hearing, March 27, 1974 (Box 5)
    - 1975-1976
      - Appropriations-Changes (Box 5)
      - Budget Request
        - Ann Arbor Campus (Box 5)
        - Dearborn Campus (Box 5)
        - Flint Campus (Box 5)
      - Department of Management and Budget Hearing, November 21, 1974 (Box 5)
      - General, 3 folders (Box 5)
      - House Appropriations Subcommittee on Higher Education Hearing, May 9, 1975 (Box 5)
      - Senate Appropriations Subcommittee on Higher Education Hearing, March 4, 1975 (Box 5)
    - 1976-1977
      - Budget Request
        - Ann Arbor Campus (Box 5)
        - Dearborn Campus (Box 6)
      - Extended Year Appropriation (Box 6)
      - General (Box 6)
      - Legislative Hearings-March 1976 (Box 6)
      - Target Budget Management Plans (Box 6)
    - 1977-1978
      - Budget Cycle (Box 6)
      - Budget Request
        - Ann Arbor Campus (Box 6)
        - Dearborn Campus (Box 6)
      - Department of Management and Budget Hearing, October 28, 1977 (Box 6)
      - Documentation, 4 folders (Box 6)
      - General (Box 6)
      - Legislative-General (Box 6)
    - 1978-1979
      - General (Box 6)
      - Legislative Hearings, 2 folders (Box 6)
      - Senate Fiscal Agency Visits, 1978 (Box 6)
    - 1979-1980
      - Documentation
        - General, 4 folders (Box 6)
        - Gerontology, Institute of (Box 6)
      - General (Box 6)
      - Legislative-General (Box 6)
      - Profiles for Legislature (Box 6)
  - 1982-1994
    The University Budget series, 1982-1994 (2.0 linear feet), is divided into two parts, 1982-1989 and 1990-1994 to maintain consistency with the office's organization of the files. The materials document the role of state government in the approval of the university's budget. The series includes files on budget analysis, appropriations bills, budget hearings, capital outlay requests, and funding strategies discussed at all-campus budget team meetings. For additional budget-related materials, the researcher may consult the Special Topical Files series.
    - 1982-1989
      - Analysis, 2 folders (Box 23)
      - Appropriations Bills (Box 23)
      - Budget Hearings, 6 folders (Box 23)
      - Budget Priorities Committee (Box 24)
      - Budget Requests, 4 folders (Box 24)
      - Budget Team (Box 24)
      - Capital Outlay, 6 folders (Box 24)
    - 1990-1994
      - Analysis, 3 folders (Box 24)
      - Appropriations Requests, 2 folders (Box 24)
      - Budget Hearings, 2 folders (Box 25)
      - Budget Team (Box 25)
      - Capital Outlay, 5 folders (Box 25)
      - Use and Finance Statements, 2 folders (Box 25)
      - Executive Order (from Governor Engler) (Box 25)
      - Higher Education Conference Committee (Box 25)
- Topical Files, 1961-1999
  The Topical Files series is comprised of four chronologically bounded ,alphabetically arranged subseries reflecting the multiple accessions through which the records were received. There is temporal overlap among the subseries and topics often extend over several subseries.
  - 1966-1982
    Topical Files, 1966 to 1982 (4.0 linear feet), is an alphabetically arranged series consisting of material related mainly to budget matters. Topics covered include the Budget Priorities Committee, Program Budget Evaluation System, Program Evaluation Committee, and University Committee on Student Fees.
    - Academic Program Inventory, 1974-1979 (Box 7)
    - Academic Staff Performance Audit, 1970-1972; 3 folders (Box 7)
    - Audit Reports
      - 1966-1973, 1 volumes (Box 7)
      - 1975-1977 (Box 7)
    - Berkley Project, 1975-1976; 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Budget Priorities Committee, 1972-1978
      - Correspondence and Memoranda, 1976-1978; 3 folders (Box 7)
      - Minutes
        - 1972-1976, 10 folders (Box 7)
        - 1977-1978, 4 folders (Box 8)
    - Budget Team, 1977-1979; 4 folders (Box 8)
    - Calendar Review Committee, 1977 (Box 8)
    - Capital Planning, Office of, 1974-1982 (Box 8)
    - Cost Study Analysis, 1972-1977 (Box 8)
    - Educational Resource Management System, 1972 (Box 8)
    - Enrollment Project, 1969-1971
      - Phase 1, February-June 1969 (Box 8)
      - Phase 2, June 1969-April 1970 (Box 8)
      - Phase 3, May-June 1971 (Box 8)
    - Expenditures, 1969-1976 (Box 8)
    - Fellowship on Internal Lateral Liaison Information, 1970-1973 (Box 8)
    - Flint Campus
      - Attrition Study, 1977-1978 (Box 8)
      - Costs, 1978 (Box 8)
    - Institute for the Administrative Advancement of Academic Women, Presentations to
      - "Fundamentals of Budgeting,", May 21, 1973 (Box 8)
      - "Institutional Process,", May 25, 1973 (Box 8)
      - "State Process,", June 4, 1973 (Box 8)
      - "Analytical Support,", June 5, 1973 (Box 8)
      - "Overview of the Budgeting Process,", June 8, 1973 (Box 8)
      - "Practicum," June 11, 14, 1973 (Box 8)
    - Library Appropriation Formula Committee, 1970-1972; 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Long Range Planning Committee, 1972-1976 (Box 8)
    - Medical and Law School Admissions, 1977-1978 (Box 8)
    - Michigan Council of State College Presidents
      - Appropriations Process Committee, 1973-1974; 2 folders (Box 8)
      - Formula Committee, 1968-1974 (Box 8)
      - Indirect Cost Group, 1973-1974 (Box 9)
    - Miscellaneous, 1970-1976 (Box 9)
    - Pending Projects, 1978 (Box 9)
    - Pharmacy, School of, Costs, 1974-1977 (Box 9)
    - Planning, 1971-1977; 3 folders (Box 9)
    - Program Budget Evaluation System
      - 1971-1972
        - Basic Program Request, October 1972 (Box 9)
        - Correspondence and Memoranda, 1971-1972; 2 folders (Box 9)
        - General, 1 volumes (Box 9)
        - Institution Program Plan
          - Ann Arbor Campus, May 1972; 1 volumes (Box 9)
          - Dearborn, Flint, Gerontology, Mental Health, 1972; 1 volumes (Box 9)
        - Program Revision Requests, August 1972 (Box 9)
      - 1974-1975
        - General (Box 9)
    - Program Evaluation Committee
      - Correspondence, 1977-1979 (Box 9)
      - Executive Committee, 1976-1977 (Box 9)
      - Membership
        - 1977-1979 (Box 9)
        - Subcommittee B, 1977-1978 (Box 9)
        - Subcommittee C, 1978-1979 (Box 9)
        - Minutes (Box 9)
        - 1975-1977, 2 folders (Box 9)
        - 1977-1979, 2 folders (Box 10)
      - Reports, 1976-1977
        - Academic Affairs, Office of (Box 10)
        - Academic Planning and Analysis, Office of (Box 10)
        - Architecture and Urban Planning, School of (Box 10)
        - Art, School of (Box 10)
        - Business Administration, School of (Box 10)
        - Dentistry, School of (Box 10)
        - Education, School of (Box 10)
        - Engineering, College of (Box 10)
        - Financial Affairs, Office of (Box 10)
        - Graduate School (Rackham) (Box 10)
        - Internal Evaluation (Box 10)
        - Law School (Box 10)
        - Library Science, School of (Box 10)
        - Literature, Science and Arts, College of (Box 10)
        - Medical School (Box 10)
        - Music, School of (Box 10)
        - Natural Resources, School of (Box 10)
        - Nursing, School of (Box 10)
        - Pharmacy, College of (Box 10)
        - Public Health, School of (Box 10)
        - Recommendations (Box 10)
        - Social Work, School of (Box 10)
        - Student Services (Box 10)
        - University Libraries (Box 10)
        - University Relations and Development (Box 10)
    - Proper Role Committee, 1970-1972; 2 folders (Box 10)
    - Public Health Statute Revision, 1976 (Box 10)
    - Sloan Project, 1974; 1 volumes (Box 10)
    - Sources and Uses of Funds, Committee on, 1975 (Box 10)
    - Steering Committee, 1972-1978; 4 folders (Box 10)
    - Student Fees, University Committee on
      - 1969-1974, 3 folders (Box 10)
      - 1974-1977, 3 folders (Box 11)
    - Tax Legislation (Tisch Amendment), 1980 (Box 11)
    - Technical Advisory Group, 1978 (Box 11)
  - 1961-1980
    Topical Files, 1961-1985 subseries (3.0 linear feet) is arranged alphabetically. Subjects for which there is thorough documentation include housing, the UM-Flint campus, minorities, and the Replacement Hospital.
    - Bookstore Proposal, 1965-1970 (Box 15)
    - Commission to Study Student Governance, 1973-1975 (Box 15)
    - Dearborn Land Transfer, 1973-1974 (Box 15)
    - Department of Population Planning, Review, 1977 (Box 15)
    - $55 Million Program, 1964-1967 (Box 15)
    - Film Showings, 1974 (Box 15)
    - Flint Campus
      - Bylaw Revisions, 1979 (Box 15)
      - Chancellor Search, 1979-1980
      - Citizens Advisory Committee, 1967-1969 (Box 15)
      - Contact with State Officials, 1974-1975 (Box 15)
      - Downtown Campus, 1964-1969; 1972-1980; 4 folders (Box 15)
      - Faculty Appointments, 1974-1979 (Box 15)
      - Grievances, 1975
      - Television Station, 1975-1980 (Box 15)
    - Gemini Spacecraft Resolution, 1965 (Box 15)
    - General Motors Stock, 1966-1970 (Box 15)
    - Genetic Detection Study, 1976 (Box 15)
    - Graduate Employees Organization Strike
      - Correspondence, 1975-1980 (Box 15)
      - GEO Proposals, 1974 (Box 15)
      - Memoranda, 1975-1980 (Box 15)
      - Negotiations Newsletters, 1974 (Box 15)
      - University Proposals, 1974 (Box 15)
    - Housing, 1968-1969; 1971-1972; 1974-1976; 1978; 8 folders (Box 15)
    - Michigan Historical Collections, 1961-1979 (Box 15)
    - Michigan Student Assembly, 1961-1979; 2 folders (Box 16)
    - Michigan Council of State College Presidents, 1969-1975 (Box 16)
    - Minorities, 1969-1979; 10 folders (Box 16)
    - Public Interest Research Group in Michigan (PIRGIM), 1972; 1975-1978; 5 folders (Box 16)
    - Recombinant DNA Research, 1975-1977; 2 folders (Box 16)
    - Regents Correspondence, 1971-1979; 9 folders (Box 16)
    - Replacement Hospital
      - 1974-1979, 6 folders (Box 16)
      - 1980-1985, 8 folders (Box 17)
    - Residential College, 1968-1970 (Box 17)
    - Reserve Office Training Corps, 1969-1970; 2 folders (Box 17)
    - Student Publications, 1962-1972 (Box 17)
    - Student Tuition Hike, 1973 (Box 17)
    - Willow Run Airport, 1972-1977 (Box 17)
  - 1968-1994
    The Topical Files, 1968-1994 subseries (6.0 linear feet), is comprised of alphabetically arranged material, with subjects indicative of the wide variety of responsibilities of the office. Topics most thoroughly documented are the office's relationship with the Michigan State Legislature and the Government Relations Advisory Committee, and Kennedy's role as the Secretary of the University found in the Regents Correspondence and Membership Reports files.
    - Alumni (includes a partial record of Kennedy's visits to alumni clubs), 1990-1993 (Box 18)
    - Ann Arbor Summer Festival (Kennedy was trustee for festival), 1978-1994 (Box 18)
    - Annual Reports, 1968-1985; 1991-1994; 3 folders (Box 18)
    - Athletic Department, 1981-1993; 3 folders (Box 18)
    - Capital Outlay, 1979-1980; 2 folders (Box 18)
    - Capital Planning, 1977-1992; 4 folders (Box 18)
    - CASE (Council for Advancement and Support of Education), 1980-1992 (Box 18)
    - Committees
      - Recognition Plaques, 1970-1977 (Box 18)
      - Records Management, 1971 (Box 18)
    - Community Affairs, 1991-1994 (Box 18)
    - Community Relations, 1987-1994; 2 folders (Box 18)
    - Dearborn Campus, 1990-1994 (Box 18)
    - Downtown Marketing Task Force, 1993-1994 (Box 18)
    - Entree Plus Program, 1993-1994 (Box 18)
    - Education, School of, 1991-1993 (Box 18)
    - Federal Relations, 1981-1990 (Box 19)
      - Indirect Costs Study, 1991-1992 (Box 19)
    - Fleming, Robben, 1974-1994 (Box 19)
    - Flint Campus, 1988; 1992
      [PR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2022; removed to vault]
    - Frye, Billy E. (Vice President for Academic Affairs), 1981-1984 (Box 19)
    - Government Consultant Services, Inc. (lobbyists for the University of Michigan), 1988-1994 (Box 19)
    - Government Relations Advisory Committee, 1990-1994; 5 folders (Box 19)
    - Graduate School, 1976; 1990 (Box 19)
    - Honors Convocation Committee, 1975-1982 (Box 19)
    - Inglis House (administered through this office), 1979-1993 (Box 19)
    - Kelsey Museum, 1986 (Box 19)
    - Law School, 1975-1989 (Box 19)
    - Medical Center (contains transcripts of Don Klaasen interviewing Kennedy), 1986-1993 (Box 19)
    - Medical School, 1979-1992 (Box 19)
    - Membership Reports, (professional memberships by department), 1984-1991; 8 folders (Box 19)
    - Michigan Awareness Program, 1977-1984; 2 folders (Box 20)
    - Michigan Collegiate Coalition, 1991-1993 (Box 20)
    - Michigan Consortium for Enabling Technology, 1988-1993 (Box 20)